It happens many times that you
apply for health insurance portability
from one insurance company to another and the
second insurance company rejects
it. So, in this section we will talk about the reasons
in which the insurance
company can reject your portability request.
A quick reminder before starting the video, if
you have not yet subscribed to our channel, do
subscribe so that you get the right
information and at the right time. And I would
like to introduce myself.
For those who are new, my name is Goodlink Kaur Tikku.
I am a Certified Financial Planner. I have been
associated with the insurance industry for the last 18 years and every week I bring you play
videos so that your personal
financial life and insurance bank
journey becomes your happy one because our
company's tagline is also creating a
wealth of happiness. Let's move on to the video. There are
4 reasons why your health insurance
portability request gets rejected first. So the biggest
reason is that you did
not provide proper documentation when you submitted the request for
portability.  So, there are
some documents required for portability,
such as your proposal
form and the portability form. Along with it, a
claim declaration goes stating whether
you had taken a claim or not,
and it is necessary to provide your existing policy copays. So, for example, if
you are
porting from company A to company B, then you will have to provide
all the documents of company A,
such as your existing policy copays, and a
declaration as to whether you have taken a claim from there or not, to the policy
holder. The proposal form will have to be filed by
dual filing, and
you will also have to provide the port form on the basis of which the
new company performs the portability exercise. The
new company verifies whether the
information you are giving is correct or not. If there is
any incomplete information or incorrect
information or incomplete
documents, then
your portability request will be rejected. That is the reason,
if you do not apply within the time limit, then there is
a time limit for portability, there is an ID on this.  You can submit a portability request within 60 days of
your policy's due date,
so for
example, if your due date is
July 31, then you have to
submit a
portability request in the window from July 1st to July 31st.
Different companies
take it at different times, so you
can submit it within this window only, you cannot submit it before that.
And this does not mean that
if the due date has passed, then after that the
insurance company does not accept portability, then
you have to apply within time only then
your portability will be accepted.
Thirdly, due to information undertaking,
your portability request can
also be rejected, that is,
when you shared your medical information in the proposal form, you
told your health conditions, what did the insurance company do,
when the insurance company evaluated
you and did the health verification, it asked you
what is your health condition, which
medicine are you taking  Let's assume that you had a
hospitalization and after evaluating it on that basis,
every company has some undertaking guidelines
that whether we
can give them a policy or not,
how will we impose a waiting period and
in portability because the risk is
from the insurance company, when you are
porting from one company to another,
then your continuity benefits are being
forwarded to the policy holder today,
but the risk of the new insurance company
starts from the de one, that is,
if you get any claim
immediately after porting, then the new
company will have to pay it, so
they have very strict undertaking guidelines
and if they discover also, then
they will see that you have a completely healthy life but the existing
conditions are minimal, then after
looking at your risk capital and looking at the
undertaking guidelines, they will
accept your portability, Advise, if it is
not set in their guidelines, if they have
bonds of their risk capital, then they will
not accept your portability  The request will be
rejected. The fourth most important
reason is that sometimes it happens that
you tried to close some non-ads with your information.
Keep this in mind that
whenever you are taking health insurance,
insurance is a contract of good faith,
so whenever you are taking insurance,
tell the insurance company in the right manner. Now
listen to me, like now when you go to
buy any insurance policy, you do the
new formalities, you
read the terms and conditions of the insurance, you
read the policy wording, you see everything, then the
insurer opens the table in front of you
in black and white, he tells you that this is
covered, this is not covered, there is a waiting
period on this, there is a spike inclusion, there is a
restriction on this, he told you everything, so it is
your duty to tell everything because it is a
contract of good faith, the
insurance company is also telling you everything
and you also tell them everything. If you are hiding something, then
you yourself will be in the middle of nowhere,
you will get
your claim.  The policy will become invalid
in the future and the insurance company has its own
agency to find out whether the
person has an existing condition or not. So,
wherever the insurance company feels that there is
distortion of facts, any
information that you had filed in the proposal form
and the insurance company has
asked you for verification or physical test, there is some
gap in it, then also your
portability request will be rejected and will
not be accepted. Here I
would like to tell that if your portability is
not accepted, then you can continue or renew your
previous insurance policy where your
previous policy was running, there is
no problem there,
your old policy is running there,
your medical conditions are already there, then
you can port there. Sometimes it happens that
you had taken a policy a long time ago, at least
10 years ago, and in
between some medical conditions are diagnosed, then
for the old company, that policy will be considered existing.  If there are
no conditions, then
you can continue with the old company,
but if the new company is rejecting portability, then
you have full right to
continue with the old policy, there will be no
problem in that. Many times it
also happens that you have
placed a request for portability, your due date has been crossed,
your due date was late, but we will
understand with examples. Today we are sitting here on 30th
of July, your due date of the policy is
30th August, you applied for portability
late on 15th August, while doing this,
medical test was done, some
documentation was asked for, your date of 31st August got over,
after the undertaking decision came,
after 31st August, the undertaking decision
came that they cancelled the portability, now
your policy is running in the grace period, the
old policy from where you were
trying to port has come
in the grace period, but still you
can renew it, if your portability request is rejected then it is
not like that  It is that the
benefits of the old policy are taken away from you,
those benefits continue,
so you can continue there and I would like to
highlight one more point, when you
port the policy in portability,
then your existing problem is that for the
time being your policy was old, but for
example, your policy was of 10 lakhs, you
put in a portability request of 20 lakhs, then
what will happen in it that ₹10 more will be
carried forward, if the portability is
accepted then the 10 lakhs above, that is,
fresh sub-increment,
whatever waiting periods are there on the policy, whatever
terms and conditions are applicable, will be applicable, your
old 10 lakh sum will be ported
and the sum will be carried forward, further it will
give you continuity from the old policy,
so these were some points that it was important to tell you
that if you are applying for any health and bravery
portability, then
what is the thing that you should keep in mind so that the portability does not get rejected, it is
important that
you have any questions  You
can share about portability in the comment section. You
can recharge us on our WhatsApp
number, email ID and there are more portability videos available on our channel, I will
put the link of that in the description box below,
you can refer to them also if you are
interested in doing portability and
before knowing, a quick reminder if you have
not yet subscribed to our channel, do
subscribe so that you get the right
information and the right time as I will still
meet you in the next video
with new information till then take care
before starting the video
because this is also the tagline of our company,
four reasons why your portability to
anything